Steven Heffner, Bassist

2 Andover Rd. Apt B3 | Athens, OH 45701 | (509) 521-0520 sheffner.2@gmail.com and stevenheffner.com

Personal Summary

I am an educator and performer with experience in arranging and composing. Versatility is key to my success and it is paramount to my philosophy of education. Through emphasizing collaboration with other disciplines, promoting musical entrepreneurship, and encouraging multi-genre musical experiences, I give my students the best possible preparation for their musical goals. As an artist, I work to provide examples of transcendent musical moments to captivate and inspire the motivations of my students as well as to fulfill my own artistic aims.

Education

cation	
2009	Master of Arts in Jazz Pedagogy
	Thesis: Approaching the Bass: A Book for Students and Teachers
	Eastern Washington University in Cheney, WA
2006	Bachelor of Music in Instrumental Performance: Bass (summa cum laude)
	Eastern Washington University in Cheney, WA
2003	Columbia Basin College in Pasco, WA
	Associate of Arts and Sciences

Professional Teaching Experience

2015-present

Adjunct Instructor, West Virginia Wesleyan College

Applied Bass Instruction

- Teach applied jazz and classical bass to music majors
- Evaluate juries, recitals, and general progress

Studio Classes

• Present weekly sessions on listening, peer performance, and group playing experiences

String Methods

 Instruct music education majors on fundamental techniques for the violin family including methods for instructing young students and beginning string programs

2013-present

Adjunct Instructor, Marshall University, Huntington, WV

Studio Classes

• Present weekly sessions on bass topics ranging from electric bass playing to classical excerpts

Applied Bass (Jazz and Classical) Instruction

- Teach applied bass to music majors
- Evaluate juries, recitals, and general progress

Jazz Improvisation Ensemble (Combo)

- Determine appropriate literature for educational and thematic purposes
- Organize concerts in conjunction with other Fine Arts departments

Jazz Theory

• Teach basic chord function through advanced reharmonization via parent scale modification, slash notation, and Coltrane changes

Jazz Improvisation II-IV

- Modify curriculum to accommodate class levels and goals
- Curriculum includes major modes, melodic minor modes, and synthetic scales as well as chordal substitutions and reharmonization in the context of jazz standards

Jazz Piano Class

- Assist in bringing jazz piano class objectives in line with current trends
- Teach basic piano and jazz theory skills
- Introduce basic concepts for shell, Bill Evans, and fourths voicings

Applied Cello Instruction

Taught cello to majors and minors in preparation for sophomore hearings

Guest Lecturer in Recreational Instruments at Ohio University 2014-2015

- Formulated curriculum to benefit interests of music therapy students
- Administered lessons in class and evaluations via recordings

2015 Guest Lecturer in Aural Skills at Ohio University

Facilitated class in sight singing and intervallic recognition

2006-2014 Private Studio Instruction

- Students ranged from adolescents to adult with varying levels of interest and proficiency
- Goals included integrating their interests with practical musical skills to provide a solid foundation for their future endeavors

2013-2014 Clinician at Ohio University

Worked with bassists on technique and fundamental walking bass line instruction

2014 Clinician at Northview High School Jazz Festival

Provided methodical instruction on basic bass methods including right and left hand skills as well as concepts for holding the bass as well as basic theory concepts for walking bass lines

Marshall University Bass Faculty for JazzMuTazz Camp 2012-2014

- Directed a jazz ensemble in rehearsal and determined appropriate literature
- Taught jazz theory
- Performed at evening concerts

Guest Lecturer in Functional Keyboard Skills at Ohio University 2012

Introduced bass lines in jazz from a bassists perspective

2011 Guest Lecturer in Class Piano for Non-Majors at Ohio University

- Generated and presented short lecture of the jazz music style
- Integrated easy blues exercises to engage basic piano skills

2008-2009 Clinics at Cheney Middle School, Cheney High School, and Central Valley High School

- Improvisation clinics determined median skill level of students, introduced simple concepts to encourage soloing in the self-conscious student, and refined the abilities of the more adventurous
- Rhythm section clinics presented on surveys of styles, idiomatic ornamentation, and understanding the role of each specific rhythm section instrument

2007-2009 Graduate Assistant, Eastern Washington University

Rock and Roll History

Co-taught lecture class on American popular music from the 1900 to 2006

Music in the Humanities

- Taught music minors and non-majors general music history spanning antiquity to 20th century
- Generated lesson plans, quizzes, and exams

Jazz Combo

- Determined appropriate literature
- Taught style and improvisation

Jazz Band III

- Rehearsed 16-member jazz ensemble three hours weekly
- Determined appropriate literature

• Organized concerts and coordinated with guest artists

2006-2008 Eastern Washington University Bass Faculty for Jazz Dialogue Camp

- Assisted with jazz bands and jazz combos
- Taught jazz theory class
- Presented master classes to bassists
- Performed at nightly faculty concerts

Professional Performances

_	2015-present	Perform with the Marshall University Faculty Jazz Octet
	2011-present	Bassist for America's Got Talent Season Six winner Landau Eugene
	2011 present	Murphy Jr., national and international touring
	2012-present	Perform in Steven Heffner Trio regularly featured at the Blennerhassett Hotel
	2012 present	with appearances by Sean Parsons, Matt James, Ryan Kennedy, and Kyle Andrews
	2012-present	Perform in Jessica Baldwin Quintet
	2013-present	Perform with Leonard, Coleman, and Blunt formerly of The Temptations, The Platters,
	2015 present	and the Drifters in regional appearances with Landau Eugene Murphy Jr.
	2014-2015	Perform with the Paramount Players Programs in multiple musicals
	2015	Performed with Jeff Bush at Marshall University Jazz guest artist concert
	2015	Performed for International Space University opening ceremonies
	2015	Performed at Athens Jazz Festival concert with guests James Moore and Jeff Bush
	2015	Performed with Maniacal 4 Trombone Quartet at Ohio University Trombone Day
	2015	Performed with Paul Johnson from Eastern Illinois University in Huntington, WV
	2014	Performed with Huntington Symphony Orchestra in Huntington, WV
	2014	Performed with Tom Walsh from Indiana University in Huntington, WV
	2014	Guest artist with Ohio University Wind Ensemble in performance of Shelly Berg's
	2011	arrangement of "Blackbird"
	2014	Performed with Jeff Bair from East Carolina University in Huntington, WV
	2012-2014	Performed with the Irish Tenors at Keith Albee Theatre in Huntington, WV, and West
		Virginia University
	2012-2014	Performed with Marietta College "Flood Stage" vocal jazz ensemble
	2013	Performed with Cave Run Symphony in Morehead, KY
	2013	Performed with Blood, Sweat & Tears in string section at Keith Albee Theatre in
		Huntington, WV
	2013	Performed with Alton Merrell of Pittsburgh at Clarksburg Jazz Stroll in Clarksburg, WV
	2013	Performed with Huntington Symphony Orchestra in Summer Season performance
	2012	Performed with Rob Parton of Chicago and Capital University at Marshall University
	2011-2012	Bassist for Sweet Basil Nonet featuring Ernie Bastin
	2011-2012	Performed with Vaughn Wiester's Famous Jazz Orchestra in Columbus, OH
	2011	Performed with Mark Pender and Richie Rosenberg at the Athens Jazz Festival
	2010	Performed with the Parkersburg Choral Society in Vienna, WV
	2009-2010	Bassist for Celebrity Cruises Jazz Quartets on Celebrity Equinox and Solstice
	2009	Performed in the West Virginia Symphony Orchestra at Clay Center in Charleston, WV
	2005-2009	Performed with Bill Holman, Matt Harris, Mike Tomaro, and Paul McKee with Eastern
		Washington University's Jazz Band I in guest artist concerts
	2006-2009	Bassist in the Don Goodwin Trio; featured at Ella's Supper Club in Spokane, WA
	2007	Performed with Hal Galper for Spokane Falls Community College Clinic
	2007	Performed with Sid Jacobs at Ella's Supper Club for Spokane Jazz Guitar
		Society concerts
	2005-2007	Performed with the Columbia Basin Jazz Orchestra in Washington State with guest
		artists including Bill Watrous and Jeff Clayton
	2006	Performed with tap dancer Arthur Duncan of the Lawrence Welk Show in Richland, WA
	2005	Bassist for Great American Cruises on the Columbia Queen in the Columbia River

Recordings	
2015	Bassist on Olivia Brownlee's track "Headin' Right In To Brighton"
2015	Bassist on Landau: Live in Washington DC
2014	Bassist on Matt James' CD "Opening Lines"
2013	Strings, bass, and horn arrangements on Central Avenue Church CD "No Other Refuge"
2012	Bassist on Landau Eugene Murphy Jr. CD "Christmas Made For Two"

Bassist on Eastern Washington University Jazz Ensemble I CD

String parts on Marshall McLean's CD "Heaven's Grey"

Bassist for American West Steamboat Company on the Empress of the North in Alaska

Honors and Affiliations:

2004

2008

2006

2011-present	Member of the American Federation of Musicians
2009-2014	Member of the International Society of Bassists
2003	Lionel Hampton Outstanding Soloist

Education/Private Instruction

Jazz/Improvisation

Todd DelGiudice: Improvisation, Jacksonville, FL

Rob Tapper: Improvisation, Missoula, MT Dominik Wania: Improvisation, Poland Jon Hamer: Jazz Bass, Seattle, WA Erik Applegate: Jazz Bass, Greeley, CO

Classical Double Bass

Kim Plewniak: Assistant Principal, Spokane Symphony, Spokane, WA

Eugene Jablonsky, Spokane WA

David Messina: West Virginia Symphony Orchestra, Charleston, WV